[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se Radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software this is Robert bloomin for
software engineering radio I am joined
by Michael hunger at Graff connect 2012
in San Francisco Michael works for neo
technology on the neo4j graph database
Michael is also the project lead for the
spring data neo4j project Michael and I
will be talking about graph databases
Michael welcome to software engineering
radio thanks for having me
Michael please tell the listeners a
little bit about your background
yeah I've been active in software
development ever since I was a kid so I
started programming and early age and
ever since I've been really interested
in programming languages computational
problems working with the people that
develop software I've been writing a lot
I've been speaking at conferences and I
try to share the knowledge I learn in my
life with other people and so the first
contact with neo4j and neo technology
was like four years ago and back then I
was really interested in what graph
databases are good for and I really got
addicted with live graphs and graph
databases like neo4j
and so I stayed and have had a really
great time ever since and I'm besides
the spring integration I also work in
the near future community team so
working with a big open source community
of developers and it's really a a great
place to be Michael will be talking
about graph databases let's start out by
talking about graphs what is a graph
so I want to start by not defining a
graph mathematically but by asking you
to look around you so devotedly living
is all about connected things so we are
connected to other people because we are
connected to events we are connected to
two things two places two actions so
it's all about relationships it's all
about connections and graphs actually
presenters information a graph consists
of nodes and relationships between those
nodes and both nodes and relationships
can quote properties at least this is
the structure of a property graph and
this data structures very immersive
tiles so it can store arbitrary
structured data and allows you to easily
model complex domains with lots of
connections and allows you to actually
navigate those relationships to gather
the information from the graph that
you're interested in if you look at it
from a historical perspective graph
theory was actually dealt with by land
euler about 300 years ago and connects
back when he looked at route routing and
path finding problems and ever since
mathematicians have been really thrilled
about graph theory
oh but graphs in your everyday on
application development are not that old
so they are not network data bases in
the 70s but actually graph databases
only appeared around 2000 and that's
where we are
no boom of craft databases so say a
little bit more about what is a graph
database a graph database is a native
storage engine that is able to store and
retrieve graph structured data meaning
nodes and relationships and properties
and nodes and relationships in a fast
and
cohesive manner so graph databases are
mostly fully transactional so do you
fully support deal the asset operations
of transactions and graph databases are
very well suited to quickly navigate
large networks of elements meaning
graphs and in general graph databases
are often different from from other
databases that we know because they have
a very distinct data model and very
distinct applications so we can use
graphs to model any kind of domain model
or object model but you can also use
graphs to execute some very interesting
operations like past finding routing
recommendation systems PageRank is
another example for that and so graph
databases support both so the usual
mapping of complex domain models and
also these specialized use cases that
graph theory is all about it's an
application that's built on a graph
database have a data model beyond having
nodes and edges yeah so every
application has a data model Dez no I
don't think there's application without
a data model and the data model is in
any case in the application and each no
sequel database the data model will
mainly decide in the application cause
most no sequel databases are schema free
there doesn't mean they don't have
structure by the structure does not live
in a database as an explicit concept but
at Linda's explicitly in the application
and the database doesn't constrain your
upfront with the structures that you
want or faked you want to have any
database but it allows you to grow and
evolve your data structure as you evolve
your application so
the data model is there it's any
application and in the graph database
itself you can retrieve or imply the
data model from the types of nodes of
relationships that are available in your
graph but it's not a closed thing but
it's kind of an open open model that can
be evolved at anytime without changing
or modifying a schema definition or
something like that Michael you said a
graph database is good at modeling many
different kinds of problem domains I can
easily see how a problem like social
graph in a social network which has the
word graph as the name of part of the
domain could be modeled as a graph but
do you see graph databases as having
broader application and possibly being a
superior model for many different types
of problems that we might not be
accustomed to thinking of as graphs if
we're used to relational databases yeah
if you look at the relational databases
so many people confuse relational
databases and relationships
what relational database is all about
relational I brought the chisel set
based algebra so there are elements of
very similar structure large amounts of
elements of the additional structure are
handled by operations like filtering and
aggregation and projection and so on
graphs on the other hand are about very
fine grained data model that's about
nodes and relationships and in general
graph databases can model complex
domains very easily and it's as they are
mostly about the Association so every
domain that has a large number of
associations of relationships benefits
from the graph model also the object the
typical object model benefits from the
graph model as well because we don't
have the very low an object-relational
impedance
as much and become if you look at our
application and use cases of the
application and we see that the
application yields will connect the data
structures with connected data then a
graph database is usually a good fit for
this kind of application should also
look at the of the data structure itself
so is the data itself connected and also
a data volume so if I have a lot of very
very simply structured data Oh
like billions and trillions of elements
then probably a key value store would it
be a bit of benefit if I have very
similar structured data in usual volumes
then like front to seller you lists a
product to store something like that in
a relational database is a benefit but
as soon as I look at connected data
Dynacraft database is usually a good fit
for this kind of application and data
structure what you're saying is choosing
the right data store then it depends on
the whether your data model is very
connection heavy and what type of access
patterns if the access patterns involve
traversing a lot of relationships then a
graph database might be the best choice
for that yes that's correct
so like in any other case of political
persistence or no see no sequel making
informed decisions about which data to
us to use derived from the data
structure that you have and also from
use cases in your application that's
what it is all about so no sequel it's
not about seeker or not sequel it's
about having a choice of databases and
choosing the right databases for your
application by looking at your use cases
in your data structure and if your data
structure and use case point to graph
databases that you would include a graph
database a new set of databases to you
if they don't have such properties and
you wouldn't want to look at the graph
databases are you seeing a lot of
application architects partitioning
their data into different subdomains
based on characteristics of the data and
access patterns and using a graph
database for one of those partitions in
relational for another one and so forth
yes actually
all we see both so we see people
partitioning their data according to
access patterns and use cases and then
using different most equal databases for
instance and graph database and in
column database um or graph database and
relational database so some people also
move out all the connection heavy data
out of their relational databases keep
poly connection and graph database like
neo4j and just keep the tabular
information in to in relational database
but you also see people that completely
move to a graph database for the whole
application and I think one of the
reasons for that is a graph database you
get the durability and atomicity on an
isolation properties of transactions and
so people trust graph databases as
they're kind of single source of truth
because they are used to these
guarantees from relational databases and
so they have easier time trusting in
graph database to become of demasters
flow of their data so I truly see lots
of different application architectures
and both are valid architectures so
there's no kind of one best way of doing
that it's always very dependent on what
you need and what you want to do and
what your experience is and so on so
there are lots of factors that influence
which way to go one of the things I have
been gradually understanding about the
no sequel world is that consistency is
more of a dial that can be turned
based on the degree of availability and
distribution in the datastore is it in
herre
the case that a graph database must
supply the acid bottle or can those
things really be considered separately
could you build a graph database that
was more base rather than acid so in
general choosing or looking at the cap
theorem and at base is mostly required
for people that have a pretty large
amount of data that he can't handle in a
single instance so they have to short or
scale out actually what we learned is
that most of the typical business use
cases don't have these large amounts of
data graph database can still support
billions of nodes of relationships in a
single instance so that's mostly not a
problem
you can easily scale out for reads by by
application and if you look into
sharding or scaling out then the
consistency dial as you said as it's
only if you look at cross the cluster so
on a single machine if you write
something to a single machine it will
still be there but if you look at the
whole cluster it takes some time to
propagate for instance to other nodes of
the cluster or other machines of the
cluster and that's the same of graph
databases as soon as you put a network
in between database instance or database
machines then you have latency about
distribution of information and having
global transactions across the clusters
of course much more expensive than
having local transactions on a single
machine
so um also near for J and now cluster
mode we have eventual consistent setups
now you can say okay I don't need fully
acid comm capabilities across the
cluster it's in okay if I have just a
right --chrome of two machines or
something like that then I write to one
machine this machine connects to another
one and they grow
and the information is synchronized on
those two machines and yato machines
have to cluster we'll get the
information propagated um so it all
depends on your needs so if you want to
have your data always consistent and
always available then you would still go
with an asset model but if it's okay for
your that you have a stale steroids for
instance then you can also of course
choose of graph database to go this
route
um that's about it application to
charting is a different aspect then you
get a graph that's so much that you
can't run it on a single instance would
you have to shot it then you get into a
very interesting problem because
shrouding graphs this an np-hard problem
especially if you have graphs that are
stored in graph data business because
those graphs are not static or dynamic
so every time you change the graph its
structure is potentially also changed
and when you try to graph you two
usually tend to take isolated sub graph
so partial to draft it has just a few
connections to the other parts of the
graph and put them on different machines
or different charts and um as soon as
you look on the database and insert new
elements and nuke relationships you of
course also change the structure of the
graph so you're kind of your charting on
algorithm while your charting
distribution that you chose at one time
might not be true at the next at the
next moment cause graph structure change
so general charting of graphs is a very
hard problem so great you're working on
that of course but in general you
usually are short on application level
so for instance when Adobe installed new
for a cluster globally they shot it by
geography class the for the US one for
Europe and one for Asia and they were
synchronized across the globe but of
course each of them was independent and
had a looser consistency approach there
Michael you said I'm gonna go that quite
often all of this significant data for
an application can fit on a single note
can you give us some approximate numbers
it for neo4j of how many nodes and edges
can be stored on a single average size
server for billion notes and thirty four
billion relationships and which will
increase to a factor of by a factor of
four or eight in the next year and this
is already beyond the needs that so far
all our customers have and did
interesting things also about the as you
said it did choice of the no sequel
database that you have for a certain use
case or the data structure implies the
database so you wouldn't use a graph
database for instance for storing very
low-level large volume dinner so you
wouldn't take a high volume event stream
and store that just in the graph
database because the graph database is
not something you would store such kind
of data in would choose a key value
store economist or to store this to
store this data in what you would store
any graph database on the other hand
would be the higher higher level
abstractions that you could retrieve or
extract from this event stream so the
model that you would derive from the low
level data that would go into the graph
database and that's what about our users
and customers to be in finance or
genetics or other sciences they look at
Leeds or telcos they look at these low
level data streams extract the relevant
and interesting information and put that
into the graph and so the data volume
data graph handles
it's much smaller and volume data
workshop data stream but it's much
richer information and also much richer
in Connexions because that's very very
actual value lies in the in this data
and then people can look at these graph
models and
make decisions run librarians on top of
that well hold up 50 citta it's graph
database more suited for applications
that are more read intensive than write
intensive that's a good question
actually
um graph databases in generally in
general are more supportive in heat
loads than in right loads because tutor
deterrents extra constrains each
transaction commit has to be flush to
disk and so if you have a high sustained
write load and then you can give you
your rights throughput is limited by the
speed of your of your disk system but
then the data is also durable so if you
have a power off in the middle of a
transaction then you don't lose any data
that's the benefit on the other end it's
optimized for reads because graph
databases also move the cost of creating
relationships to insertion time so
social time when we say you and me fans
with a connected disk relationship said
she stored and graphed in a base as a
record but that makes reading of
following connections or relationships
very fast because there's just a record
that I can take and and follow and I
don't have to recreate the connection
body pulling tables or lists of elements
into memory and finding matches and then
from those matches direct connection at
CROI time so that's why the very part is
much faster on a graph database and
we've also seen that graph databases can
for instance execute join heavy queries
up to a thousand times faster than a
relational database and so you're right
in your assumption that graph databases
are more suitable for big loads and wide
loads I would characterize a relational
database in terms of career performance
as
the number of rows it can consider and
the number of tables involved how do you
measure or quantify the read performance
of a graph database in general as graph
databases are about local fairies so you
take one or more starting points for
instance users or products or movies or
songs or something like dental places
and from those starting points you
navigate a graph so the navigation so
Jay gives you help from one element from
one node to another it's a constant time
operation because we have the pre
computed and pre-stored relationship
records so Ukraine's actually only
depending on the number of elements you
touch during the traversal so from the
traversal depth and breadth so depends
your very performance but doesn't impact
your trade performance is the total size
of the graph or the total amount of data
because you always have local fairies so
you're not interested how many other
people are living in the world if you
just like want to retrieve some
information from your friendship graph
for instance and you're also not
interested in how many products are in a
certain data warehouse if you just want
to compute the combination for a certain
category something like that so high
performance in the graph database is
determined by the number of steps you
take in your navigation of the graph
that's the only thing that determines
the correct performance and both data
volume and join complexity does not
impact the performance in in a negative
negative say Michael I think it might
help us all to understand this graph
model if you could give us an example or
maybe a toy example of a problem from a
business domain and how it would get
mapped into a graph
abstraction yes so there are lots of
business events you could choose from
let's take a movie database as an
example
so um I have in a movie database I have
movies I have actors I have directors I
have users
I have roles that actors played in a
movie
I have ratings I have previews comments
and so on so all of these are elements
and all of those could and elements are
connected so let's look at the main
elements which are the movie which will
become a note the properties like title
and publication year and so on then we
have the actors which are also notes
with their names and birthdays and so on
the relationship between a movie and
directors actually interesting because
this role which would end up in a
relational database as a joint table
most probably will just become a
relationship between the two and all the
information about the role like the the
money got and the role name and the
whatever other information is on that
would live on this relationship and this
relationship could be for instance an ex
in relationship between the actor in the
movie so I could say this actor X in
this movie and that defines the
relationship type which is X direction
from actor to movie if I look at the
other elements front of the user the
user can be false as friend of other
users so if user have France
relationships to other users and then
use a quote from some great actor a
movie so whatever be also in a rated
relationship going from their user to
the movie and from the user to the
reactor and the rated relationship could
for instance contain also information
like how many stars you give the movie
or a comment on the movie or something
like that and have all these things in
place we then can say ok we can easily
build a movie database application on
top of that because I just have all my
elements in place all my objects are all
my types I
after graph mapper like it's prettier
than you for j4 retrieving for
retrieving the data from from the
databases to an impact so just basic
crud operations and that gets
interesting is when I want to for
instance compute recommendations for
users so I want to see which movies
could I recommend to this user to watch
right so I could for instance see look
at the friendship graph of this use and
and see which movies his friends like
and recommend to top 10 movies yeah but
I could also see him look at the movies
a user rated positively look at other
people which also rated these movies
positively so which was kind of similar
to this initial user and then look at
those movies that those users also liked
and did our our initial user has not
seen yet so that's a typical
recommendation a burden which is also
called collaborative filtering and so
I've tried to find similar people and
then I look for those similar people
with a date or like and that's kind of a
two-line expression in a graph and would
be a very complicated joint in a
relational database and very expensive
journal and it's really really fast to
do this something like this with craft
database that's a simple example of how
you can employ a graph database tomorrow
your application and your domain the
query examples that you're giving
Michael I find them quite interesting
because those queries would be difficult
to do in sequel would probably involve
writing some kind of logic that mixed in
a programming declarative programming
language with a series of sequel
statements and unpacking the results
whereas you can do that natively in a
graph database very efficiently well
once you get your mind around these type
of queries does that change your design
and thought process of how you think
about the application
yes it usually does it moves your
thinking more around the the use cases
so you go away from just thinking about
data structures to what you want
actually what to achieve and then this
also allows you to for instance add
additional relationships to your domain
model that support you in your use cases
so for instance if I get another use
case in that's nice I don't just want to
recommend movies to people but I also
want to I recommend people to movie
studios or labels because I have fun
sense in my database of any good on set
of people that are very interested in
movies and that could be a good set of
converse for movies right so I would
turn the whole thing around and say okay
I have to say existing model and it's
clearly very easy to just turn the car
around and say I'm not looking at the
movie anymore but I'm looking at people
on my graph and I can for instance
create recommendation sets for movie
labels from people that would be really
valuable for that either by for for
advertisement or for beings of yours for
their movies so that having the data in
the graph allows me to add another level
of use cases very easily and it also
allows me to add other domains very
easily so for instance if I add to this
movie database location so I know the
location for and some of my users and I
can do all the local event cinema going
to movies for friends thing very easily
just by adding this geo information well
if I add another part of the domain like
TV series or something like that then I
can easily add to the recommendations
that I make for people what to do
tonight and not just going to movies but
also just watching or something that I
have wanted to watch but I didn't know
on TV right so it's um adding more
domains to a graph makes it actually
richer and allows it to answer more
interesting questions which of
more valuable answers actually when you
start thinking about problems in this
way does that change how you think
that's an excellent question actually
good question is if how you think
affects how your data model looks like
or how your data model affects your
thinking because if you look at whenever
they are working creatively so when we
discuss things with people when you go
to a whiteboard and we brainstorm then
be doodle then via design things and so
on you often tend to draw graphs on our
whiteboards or on our sheets even mind
maps are graphs and so that got me
thinking of kind of the graph like
thinking is more part of the creative
process and if the kind of D tabular and
list based structure of relational
database is more kind of the data
management logical part of of our left
hemisphere kind of Saudi kind of
analytical part is more the ad tables
and lists and the creative part is more
data graphs and visualizations and
complex and interesting networks thing
so that got me thinking if somehow this
is all related and of course our brain
is also a big big Network so we have a
graph in our head as well we've been
talking about near for J water what are
some of the more popular graph databases
out there in the market cluding open
source yeah so actually near for J is an
open source graph database and has been
around for a while
also it started development of neo4j in
2000 as part of a content management
system actually and fast and pulled out
later and so there are quite a number of
crafty devices around and you see new
graph databases popping up every other
week so 2012 has been the year where we
have seen a huge increase in the number
of graph databases so
autograph databases are oriented be
death decks there's infinite graph from
objectivity
there is also hyper graph to be deaths
Titan there's for Microsoft just Trinity
frog DB from Twitter
there are graph databases internal graph
databases at Google and other companies
there is pray after hardware based graph
compute engines
there are crafts processing frameworks
based for instance and I do and that's
can lead a large ecosystem of graph
databases out there people can look at
and choose what do you think is
responsible for this rapid growth of
interest in graph databases at this time
that's a very interesting question so I
think one of the main drivers for the
interest in graph databases this that
right now we are trying to derive more
value from the connections between
people are things so first of all we
started exploring the personal social
networks of people that but that easily
extends to other places it extends to
their workplaces so we've seen new types
of job applications coming out it
extends to their buying behavior of what
to do it what do I like fix like
Pinterest and so it also extends to it
to the places we are like if you look at
Foursquare for instance that's
location-based services it's all about
having people and things being connected
to each other it's also about the idea
more and more available information
devices all around us the Internet of
Things and so on so it's the kind of the
focus on moves from individual items
which kind of looked at just atomically
to the network of or the rich network of
interconnected
and to handle these kinds of data you
need a database that is able to store
and look 50 so efficiently and so do you
need interesting graph databases
it's obviously driven by this need to
focus on the relationships much more
than just the individual elements and
also if you look at something like the
Google knowledge graph so there's so
much information and knowledge hidden in
the connections between things which can
also improve the quality for instance of
search results or the quality of
algorithmic results by orders of
magnitude so Google employed lots of
people and lots of hardware are lots of
algorithms and to improve the search
results by developing the Google
knowledge graph for instance which kind
of takes search to the next level and
that's kind of a trend that started
three years four years ago and the kind
of increase exponentially over the next
few years so there will be more time
crafting a basis bigger graph databases
and I think all the everyone will have a
graph database what are some of the
differentiating factors between the
different graph databases in general
there are factors the differentiate a
business on the audit data model so new
for J and most of the other popular
graph databases employed a profit
property graph which is north central
ation ships with properties on both then
there are the RDF triple store graph
databases like a Lego graph and lots of
scientific projects which store triples
of data like subject predicate object
instances and they are very well used in
the whole
semantic web link Data initiatives and
also at universities and so on and
there's another graph model that is
called the hyper cross model where a
relationship doesn't just connect to
nodes but an arbitrary
which is suitable for certain kind of
certain kind of problems so what you've
seen so far is that people tend to get
their head around property craft model
most easily because it's very similar to
the object model if people were close
and Anna differentiators between graph
databases is if they're able to dispute
or not some graph databases additional
capabilities like awkward to be wants of
provides an object I'm sorry a document
few on the graph other graph databases
have certain characteristics in in data
volume query time it depends on kind of
on what the different vendors wanted to
focus on something like neo4j is more a
general-purpose versatile graph database
that you can do everything with but you
might for certain problems at the kind
of edges of this problem domain much
with different products for that and
yeah so then another furniture is of
course being open so also closed source
so things like neo4j going to be
tightened for instance open source
crafted a basis and others like infinite
graph Allegra graph a commercial
proprietary graph databases which are
not open source and then there's of
course also differentiators on terms for
instance of community engagement but
it's not
is there anything like standardized
query language that most graph databases
support or does each one take its own
approach to queries yes era of crafted
abysus was still pretty young it took a
while for the sequel standard to evolve
and so the graph databases at some point
will also evolve
is that not right now everyone has its
own solution so there's 20 of Ajaib you
have a graph query language is called
cipher oh you had to be for instance
supports a sequel like trading which
other databases on the support things
like a data model Prolog as training
which is um
Desa framework an open-source framework
that is kind of provides the minimum api
of a property graph database which is
called
blueprints and there's a query language
an imperative language sitting on top of
that which is called gremlin and many of
the property graph databases support
this it's actually a DSL and sitting on
top of an API it's not a kind of textual
trade in which per se so it's a groovy
based DSL for a kind of minimum common
API across graph databases but beyond
that oh yes so my how do you evaluate
the ecosystem as far as mapping tools
between the programming language and the
database or maybe I should start out
saying is is there a need for a a
mapping layer to help the programmer
persist their objects into the database
[Music]
first this question two parts the first
is the the problem on how to talk from
programming language of your graph
database in general that of course
depends on the API did graph database
offers and on the community so we were
quite fortunate in near future as open
source community they have a lot of
people providing drivers for their
programming languages most of the
programming languages that are out there
for you today
both for the JVM embedded version of
Netaji as well as the silver version and
other databases have similar approaches
so that you have kind of the low-level
access is the driver for your language
that's the kind of the first requirement
that you have to fulfill to total de
Graaff database and secondly the mapping
tools it's an interesting question it
seems that people want to have those so
it is kind of a a boilerplate effort to
write a mapping on your own and so like
50 national databases Road people wrote
after relational mappers
people also bright object graph my purse
um spring that I knew for J's for
instance one example of an object graph
mapping tool yeah number of others as
well um yeah it depends so it's kind of
more of a convenience so you could of
course write this on your own in a
limited amount of time to kind of cover
the needs that you have but there are
actually some tool tools around it and
so people seem to like it and seem to
use it but they should be also always
aware that putting an indirection layer
between a graph database and your actual
oberyn's doesn't help those high
performance things like massive data
ingestion or extraction well graph
accordance you should really have
Randall's things within the database not
pull the data out and run it outside but
it's really convenient for simple
integration with other libraries for for
UI frameworks and for basic crud
operations it's quite a nice fashion
object are there any other aspects of
the graph database ecosystem you're
aware of that people should look into if
they're using a graph database yeah what
really interesting aspect of graph
databases is they don't really
visualization heavy so um a graph in
general
has the nice property of being mapable
from a fun sense from a whiteboard
drawing directly into the database so if
you stand by a whiteboard for some
colleagues or a domain expert at discuss
your domain and the elements and
relationships that are on your domain
and draw something that everyone agrees
on you can put a data and graph and then
you visualize it
it's a actually the exact same
representations you had on a whiteboard
so it has no kind of mismatch or
transfer loss of information between a
drawing which is also graph at the
database a fun fact of that is that even
relational databases model the data
structures as graphs or each entity
relationship diagram that we've seen is
actually also a graph database but in
general the visualizing what is in your
graph database is a very important thing
to take a few users so people tend to
have a lot of visualization interests in
visualization options and there are lots
of frameworks out there for visualizing
graphs there's gaffi which is a Java
based framework there is a lot of
JavaScript based framework solutionizing
graphs like these three for instance or
Sigma GS and this is a very very
important aspect so people always asked
for how do I visualize my data how can I
see what's in the graph how do I can
kind of Reason about it and how can I
find patterns in the graph by just
looking at it and that's kind of also
what I spoke about before these kind of
higher level information that you
extract out of low level information put
it into the graph and then you can
visualize it and then you can easily see
something like clusters outliers or
dense connections or important hubs in
your graph and so on so there's a really
easy way of kind of
first glimpse of the data that you have
any graph with visualization so the
ecosystem or visualization tools is very
very large and craft your business
another important aspect of course and a
differentiator is graph I burn so there
are lots of different graphic burdens be
it for path finding for routing for
collaborative filtering recommendation
systems things like page rank or a
burdens for predicting follow for
instance language analytics we had a
project from some young students in
Germany which ingested the Google Ngram
data of probabilities into a graph
database actually a VJ and we were able
to predict the next word following the
current one with a high very high
probability so something like that it's
also possible so the whole area of graph
our this is also something that kind of
differentiates graph data based from
other databases and gives you a really
high leverage because for a good
algorithm you can kind of beat your
competition easily but for deriving a
certain information out of your data or
certain value from your data and there's
also kind of different support of graph
algorithms across the databases and but
you can also easily just read about them
implement them on your own and that's
pretty easy to do with most graph
database API is so it's not kind of like
rocket science to does the user of graph
database need to understand the graph
algorithm that the server will be using
to do a particular query or operation it
depends on the use of course usually
don't they don't have to understand it
because they can easily formulate what
they want to have of what you want to
see by just specifying a pattern in the
graph so imagine you have a graph of
users having rated movies
we talked about before then you can
easily specify a pattern that you would
say okay starting from this user I want
to see or I want to go to all the movies
that he rated and from those movies I
want to go to all the other users that
also move or edit these movies and from
doors I want to go to the actors that
they might or something like that you
just kind of specified a pattern or the
past that you're interested in and
that's kind of nowhere near a graphic
room but it's already very very powerful
in allowing you to derive the
interesting information under the graph
only if you have really are specialized
problems like Constance routing or so
then you should be aware about that our
graph algorithms for routing but what
you actually do is just you supply the
start and the end node of your of your
routing problem like you're two cities
you want to connect and then you just
tell the database to go ahead and
provide you the two top five shortest
ways between those two cities and that's
about it so most of the graph algorithms
themselves you don't have to understand
them you just need to know what is their
kind of API what do they expect us input
values and then they provide you with
the pass through graph a lot of
information that you can use to solve
your actual business problem tell us a
little bit about neo4j the product that
you work on you for J's for yeah so um
you forget actually one of the oldest
graphing events and was one of the
biggest so it has a pretty large active
community a large customer base as well
you've grown from ten people when I
started to more than 50 now within a few
years and me for J is a native graph
database so we have our own native
storage engines or it's not sitting on
top of some other product product and
it's reading Javas or utilizes
JVM so it's also portable across
platforms and can be embedded in other
java application which is really a nice
feature for both high-performance
applications and also for
and testing as well um you can get
started with need for jail very easily
if you have a website me for Jared walk
that gives you lots of information and
lots of cream costs and videos we have
also a manual that is actually quite
interesting the causes not just a manual
but it's also generated from tests so
it's not just verbal text but it's then
running tests we generate code snippets
results the presentations graphs and so
on from passing unit tests that will end
up being chapters and sections of the
manuals so you're always up to date and
the kind of information of any manual
which is really convenient very very
nice and that's also very large user
community around here for J's or lots of
people on the Google Group on Stack
Overflow and so on as I said you have
two big advantage that there are many
universes users who felt a need for a
driver for neo4j in their own specific
programming language and if there wasn't
one they just started to write one and
most of those they're actually using it
for Jane production or customer projects
so their drivers are words of really
high quality so that's a really big
advantage of being an open-source
database so defi you didn't have to
invest lots of people and lots of effort
to develop and support all these drivers
on our own but people that are the
experts in those languages were able to
write those queries for a future so
being an open-source database with a
very active community is a really great
place to be in and to work with and so I
would encourage everyone to just grab a
copy off of neo4j take one domain model
that you're interested in and play
around with it try to visualize it fifty
integrated visualized
we run some creds on top of that and
imagine and how it could look like in
the next project or application to use a
graph database and I also want to
encourage everyone to kind
open your eyes and look at the world by
looking at the connection between things
and not so much the things themselves
and to see how much of our everyday life
is actually basic graphing is connected
of course it gets really addictive if
you start doing that and tell us about
your open source project the spring data
neopor J yeah premiered on e for J is
it's the founding project of the
strength data project which is an
initiative bus print source to provide a
convenient access layer to the many know
sequel databases that are out there so
we know that all spring source has done
a good job at providing a convenient
accessory to relational databases with
the JDBC abstractions and also DHAP
obstructions and so if en vias premises
this Prem data project is a quite
important strategic project and it was
actually started by Rob Johnson and my C
or mal sitting together discussing those
seek for discussing the elements of
sequel for spring and starting to work
and actually code on the first situation
on this printer in the fridge a project
which is quite interesting so it started
the whole movement and it's pretty
linear for J itself is an object graph
mapper so it takes you two main objects
that you imitate similar to GP objects
you just annotate your objects and then
a spinner neo4j offers you a very
convenient and straightforward mapping
from those objects into the graph so you
can easily create you the main model in
as Java classes where properties of the
class or fields of the classes are
mapped into either properties of the
nodes or actually references to other
objects are mapped with relationships to
other nodes in the graph database and
relationships are also first-class
citizens in the graph database so they
on spinning foj and
so you have a really easy way to
integrate the craft in a place with
existing libraries with your eye
frameworks and the other places in its
print ecosystem as well but you have at
all time the ability to drop down to a
lower level API which gives you d do
high performance graphics which are not
impacted by the intermediate layer and
springier neo4j
also offers a really nice repository
approach that orders printed a project
support which allows you to write data
access layer without actually writing
code by just defining interfaces with
methods and on those methods you can
either have the infrastructure
automatically derived decrease that they
stand for like in grades or Rhea's all
your annotated methods 50 Kreis you want
to execute so it's very thin and
convenient layer for except of
abstracting the excess of the underlying
database via such a repository approach
and it opens was apache license project
part of the Spring Framework as printed
a project project and actually happy
booking the VM there and it Springs
those engineers on that and it has
gotten quite a lot of traction and even
some of our bigger customers actively
using it pointed I knew forge a to
develop their business application sort
of neo4j
Michael tell us about how the near forge
a open source project is structured and
what role is served by neo technologies
where all does the community play near
forget in itself is an open source
project it is available on github so all
these source code development is
publicly visible as fellow so issue
tracking and so on neo technology
supports the project by employing the
engineers that work on neo4j
but we always welcome contributions from
the community
we actually are very interested in our
community because they provide us a
really great feedback and support for
neo4j
so we're getting a lot of meaningfully
our first class on feedback back from
our community and near 4j is also
licensed with an open-source license so
neeraj a community edition is licensed
with GPL version 3 so it's similar to
mice mice equal and near for junior
enterprise license is licensed under GPL
so when you're open source vo also open
source and live then you commercial then
you can acquire a commercial license for
enterprise but you can also go over the
community and run your server side
project on your project Community
Edition and being an open-source project
we also put out all our content under
credit Creative Commons license so we're
very liberal what the interaction and
collaboration
oh it's about and something that's also
great about a community a rich community
is that you have a lot of local meetup
groups so right now we have I think in
28 cities around the world via local
neo4j meetup groups and if you want to
grow that so that we cover most after
areas and everyone can find it locally
near forge a meetup group nearby to
discuss and exchange ideas and give
feedback and learn new things and be
creative and interactive yeah so I must
say personally I really love working
with in an open-source project because
that's a really incredible place to be
Michael if listeners would like to learn
more about neo4j how can ad down so
there's a lot of content about new for J
out there so we have a website that knee
rotate at work also a block and we have
lots of video online
online from our conference from graph
Connect which we want to repeat in 2013
in lots of different places from our
meetup groups so as I said we have these
all these local meetup groups which are
really great who is also a great place
to learn from our Google group so we
have a very active group there people
can ask questions other people all
explained graph concepts or have done
and also on Stack Overflow down a lot of
questions about me for Jay and also
death as well and if you also run
regular webinars every week or every
other week about topics around graph
databases in neo4j also customers case
studies and custom reports and easiest
way is just to Google for neo4j and then
follow all this information is and read
about it and best of all it's not spy
get your copy of me over gah read out
and get going that's the best way of
getting rough after wall
Michael listeners would like to follow
you or your work where do you publish on
the Internet ah
so I myself I publish my things at GE x
period of the year but nowadays most of
my blog posts go actually to blocked on
your fridge edit works as part of the
community team I tend to write a lot of
blocks and more blocks and community
than personal loss these days Michael
thank you very much for speaking to
software engineering radio
[Music]
thanks for listening to su radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
dash radio net to support us you can
advertise su radio by clicking the de
crédit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about this on
Facebook Twitter or your own blog if you
have feedback specific to an episode
please use the commenting feature on the
site so that other listeners can respond
to your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]